some questions that we had from the dot
zero but also new questions arising
so we'll just start with an introduction
and saying hello and then it'll be
awesome to hear the author's initial
contextualization so i'm daniel i'm a
researcher in california and as explored
a little bit in the dot zero with sid
there's a few places that we were super
curious about ranging from how does one
go from a phenomena that they want to
model like navigation to the analytical
equations and how is that related to
active inference in the free energy
principle and then how do we go from
that analytical formulation
to the actual gigabyte of video data and
the real-time sensing and actions so a
lot of exciting topics and i'll pass to
blue
hi i'm blue i'm a researcher in new
mexico and um this paper was kind of way
over my head
for a lot of reasons it's just so far
out of what i normally do
but i have some questions related to the
hierarchical modeling and how that is
kind of used and
how that can be related or cannot be
related to maybe biological systems that
model in a hierarchical way similarly um
and i'll pass it off to adam i guess if
you want to start or introduce yourself
and and you guys can take it away
uh hi i'm adam i'm a systems
neuroscientist who's
uh currently a research fellow at the
johns hopkins center for psychedelic and
consciousness research
um
i've been collaborating with tim and
ozin and others on
trying to
understand the natures of navigation
and
the nature and the ways in which the
hippocampal and enter rhino system might
be relevant
and the ways in which this could be used
as a means of understanding
um
thought more generally
and it's been uh
awesome and slightly intimidating except
tim is awesome so that's made it less
intimidating
so that brings it to me so i'm tim um
i'm a computer scientist roboticist at
kent university
and we haven't subscribed to the active
entrance formalism to
try to make our robot
slightly more intelligent um
this paper was i think one of our
major accomplishments last year into the
collaboration with
adam where we basically
look at the problem from
of navigation from from different angles
ranging from
active inference modeling
to an actual implementation
on a real robot
and at the same time looking at
how
could this work in in an actual brain or
or what other
relations uh and the synergies there so
it's really exciting uh
to have this paper out but also this was
just as getting started i'd say it was
it was basically our first
um artifacts that we
published we have another one
together with adam in the works
um and yeah
i'm pretty sure that we will continue
this endeavor for for quite some time
london so we're all just only just
getting started so
uh that being said but
probably a lot of the questions are also
still questions for us
so we'll see uh to what extent we can
give give an answer as of today already
awesome well we can
start with this sort of
triad that is
highlighted in the paper
and adam you said it as understanding
the basis of navigation and we have
these three legs to the stool kind of
three threads that intertwine in the
paper with it analytical
formulation of navigation which is what
blue mentioned with a hierarchical
generative model
and the implementation in robotic and in
biological
systems so maybe a first question is
how has this
intersection
of modeling navigation with robotics and
biology been conceptualized and what
brought you to apply active inference in
this way and what does it add
we should go first
[Music]
so
so maybe my my perspective here is that
um
we basically got started from um
from a robotics perspective like looking
at
the the navigation problem and looking
at the
ways that it's being solved
right now
and implemented right now
and at the same time we already had
quite some experience with active
inference but more like
on yeah
simpler problems let's say or first
or first experiments were more on this
kind of
mountain core
environment or simulated car racer but
it was always our goal to kind of try to
scale it up to
yeah to real-world robots
and so
we got started by
drawing and seeing barrels between
current implementations out there
that seem to match with with how we
would look at it from an active
inference perspective
and
kind of work our way from both ways so
on the one lens try to get some
implementation running and on the other
hand
seeing how we could
formalize it and and actually make the
mouth work in the active inference
framework
and
what we found out was that actually the
the best matching um
implementation from a robotics
perspective was actually one that was
quite bio-inspired so it was basically
the the red flag model from milford at
all
where they had these
uh heavy inspiration from grid cells
place cells and these things
and yeah of course uh
it was not really a surprise given the
the fact how active entrance is also
grounded in in neuroscience and so
that's where we reached out to to
um
to basically show off like okay
this is our trajectory uh this is our
plan this is our current implementation
and how we think the math could work
um and then adam
with his infinite knowledge on
how the the the
the
it could work in the brain he gave like
all kind of pointers like okay but this
is interesting because what you
implemented here is actually
looking a lot a lot like this kind of
system and what you're doing here is
actually
very much like these kind of things and
then we just said okay let's let's dig
into this further and
and we basically uh started on curving
out
um
ping-ponging like okay if this is how
it's done in the brain and maybe we can
make something more similar in in the
mouth or in the implementation vice
versa
and
the paper is basically a first step
where we had like
the three bits kind of in place but we
know where the open issues are
but it actually has something working on
on an and sensible on all three uh
levels i'd say uh and that's that's
that's where we we
we are at
at this moment
awesome thank you adam anything you um
add to that
i guess what i would add is um
i'm
increasingly uh
compelled by the idea that
um
robotics as a touchstone and basis for
understanding different aspects of mind
is
like it might be the most powerful kind
of um
grounded empiricism we can do
and i i think it's both because it's
like the like a lot of times like that
feminine quote of like what i cannot
build i cannot understand is like
mentioned but this is actually building
systems that yeah this is
that that have to work and um and
that these problems
like in going through them and looking
at the different solutions
like the kind of understanding you get i
think is really uh unique
but also i think it's particularly apt
because
of what our minds other than controls
cybernetic control systems for
bodies that have to move through the
world
and so this idea that like the way
roboticists are approaching it like
it's
and
that is
the exact problem that nature had to
solve but natural selection had to solve
now the question is was it the same it
might be in some cases because you'd
expect you know um within you know
bounds
uh
nature to be a fairly clever uh blind
designer um
in terms of what it might discover and
so
just this going back and forth between
the the robotics perspective
and the how it might work in biology and
then this abstract ways that they're um
the abstract algorithmic implementations
of them for the robots
and seeing how those can mutually inform
each other it's
i mean for me it's uh
this is how i basically want like all my
thinking about the mind to be from now
on like i feel like this is just like
this is how it has to this is the most
powerful way of thinking on it
that back and forth
let's enter in the biological door or
blue do you have a question
okay
so
adam
what
even though of course it's a deep area
and there's writing in the paper and
citations and so on
what is so interesting about the
structuring of the grid cells through
space and time
and what can we learn from that about
effective ways of navigating
so
in in leighton slam um
we have these pose cells and actually i
think um
probably better for tim to talk about
that like the exact ways in which these
cells function within the robotic system
i think that actually brings more
clarity
than um the more mysterious like so
there's lots of ideas been going around
like computational neuroscience of like
what the grid cells might do
but i actually think the greatest
clarity comes from like well how would
the analogs work in the robotic system
so i'm going to kick that to tim uh what
do you think tim
yeah so i
i think that in
in our current implementation
the
the parallel with grid soles is kind of
um
part wired in the implementation it's
kind of
this by design you have something that
looks
if you squint your eyes a lot
it looks a bit like grip so i i wouldn't
say that we actually have
um grid cells in here
um
because to me the grid stuff is
basically
it should be an abstract
it should be
um giving you a way of
modeling movement in an abstract space
basically
and in the case of navigation
the space
by accident maps to the real world
and
the grid selectivation is just a a
peculiar way of
encoding
where you are in space
without um
without just giving you the x y
coordinates basically
with a more kind of
um
uh
higher dimensional
more robust representation of
where are you on in this on this grid
and how do you if i now move
how does how does your
location in in
in this reference frame or this
uh change
and so in our in our implementation we
basically just said okay we know that we
are in a
roughly flat uh surface world
so
the main coordinates that we need to
track and integrate over are the x
x y position and um
the head direction these are basically
the the main things
and then we we
use this thing called the continuous
director network to kind of
represent
these three coordinates
and
we basically
um um
we inject the knowledge that if you move
forward then
um
you will also move forward within this
uh
attractor network uh
location and
roughly this this corresponds to doing
kind of bulk integration and i'm pretty
sure that grid cells are um
giving you similar functionality um in
the brain that i would not say that our
current implementation actually has grid
tools i think the parallel is more
with place cells
because there we do have kind of we do
learn
representations from
visual sensory inputs
that kind of
give you an an
estimate of
this is a particular location
and if you see a similar pattern
then
it is likely that you are visiting the
same location again
and it
at the same time you happen to have a
very similar
x y uh and head direction as in your uh
as in your previous time you you you
kind of saw something still like that
then you have pretty good evidence that
you are actually in the same
spot and then uh this is what you then
call a loop closure and then you kind of
reorient yourself
as if you were at the same location so
that's kind of how
i would uh
think of uh
grid cells and place cells in in our
current in our current work
thank you blue do you have any
questions yes please go for it
so i'm i'm curious as to um
the role if any or how the system may
change um if you included proprio
reception which is like
the sense of where your
body is in space and so like this is
partially modeled through the visual
system um at place cells grid cells etc
but it's it's not always right so it
includes other senses like balance and
you know where is my hand and these
kinds of things um and i'm just curious
if your model
includes that in any way or um only
or or not or how it may change if it did
um give it kind of like a more embodied
um
yeah so so basically uh in our case the
proprioception is limited to
um
basically the the
the velocity commands that you that you
issue to the to the robot it also
observes these again so it assumes that
it knows which command sending and then
these are also kind of
fed back to the model as kind of a
sensor so if you say drive forward or
turn left or turn right with these kind
of angular velocities this information
is also sent
into the model and this is then what we
call the action so everywhere in the
especially in the low level model you
see the action pop-up this is basically
you can you can see this as kind of a
proprioception uh
thing and so everything
kind of predicts
what will happen
given um given what i
i sensed that i was doing basically
um
and we do it both for the for the visual
sensor like what would i see if i if i'm
turning left or right or go forward
but also for
tracking the the pose and doing the
pattern integration like if i move
forward and my heading was a zero angle
then i will probably just move forward
in the x direction of the of the
um
and that introduction of counter
factuals and anticipation what would
happen if i did this
is very interesting area and uh
also it it
speaks to the composability and the
flexibility of the active inference
model like sid highlighted that only the
visual data were being used here with
the rgb
values of video but there are other
kinds of sensors
that could be
used as another sense state and that
would kind of increase the
dimensionality of the model maybe it is
a value add maybe it's not but it
doesn't require um re-writing it's like
more like plugging in a different hard
drive than it is like having a different
computer
um
so
you mentioned a higher dimensional
robust representation of location
and that's definitely one of the
advantages and and aspects of the model
that'll be important to
explore more like in the dot zero we
explored this paper are we ready for
service robots
that showed how sometimes even trivial
changes to environments can result in
the robot getting lost because it has
referenced to something like a chair
that's no longer at the same location
so
how
does this model
provide a higher dimensional robust
representation of location
and
how did you go from thinking about that
to the actual way that the
generative model is framed
that's the first question and then the
second part is going to be about how do
you go from the framing to the actual
computational implementation but just
the first stage of this pipeline how do
we go from um wishing upon a star that
we could have biologically inspired
resilient navigation
to writing down the formalisms as you
had them
yeah so
to get back at yours at your first
at the problems that you
that you mentioned on the
on the service robot like so basically
the the major problem in in robotic slam
is that
indeed if your environment changes uh
slightly a bit then
then
the same location doesn't look the same
anymore in whatever sensor modality
you're using and
that can be problematic especially if
you if you want to model
the uh the environment as like a metric
system where you basically
um
define this is my origin so this is zero
zero in the coordinate system and now i
will
for every obstacle or
thing that i approach i will log my
estimation of the x y coordinates
and and then suddenly when your chair
moves of course yeah it
everything breaks
but here and in in this system
we actually
get rid of
being grounded in in in the metric space
the only thing that matters is that
this location looks very similar to
something uh i i visited before and it
also seems likely given the the pet
integrated um
trajectory i i assume i was following so
this might be the same spot
and if you think that or if the chair
moved
in in that place
yeah that's fine then you just say okay
maybe it's a different spot it doesn't
really matter
um
at some point
you will have a kind of a queue that is
stable right so and that's actually what
we also do as as humans if you want to
navigate you just look for the the the
queues that you are that you know that
are pretty stable if you visit a new
town you will look for the church tower
because you know it will not move you
will not
orient yourself based on the core of the
cars that are parked
somewhere so
i think
by by
using the active entrance
principle as as
as like a starting point
you can you can get rid of all
a lot of these these problems because
your agent will automatically
um
look for these stable cues and if
suddenly the environment changes but
just accept this and just model it as
like okay i i
i think i i'm revisiting this same
trajectory but now it looks different so
maybe i just have to model it as such as
this is kind of a trajectory that can
change often and maybe this implied
that
if you plan the next time you'd rather
prefer a different trajectory where you
know that everything is stable right so
this is the
the the same as as reducing your your
ambiguity so i i think that getting rid
of
everything should be structured in this
x y location
in the metric space and else i don't
know what's going on just by getting rid
of that and and
just assume anything can happen anything
can change and if it does not change i i
prefer it i like it better
this helps a lot
to circumvent a lot of the traditional
problems i've seen
cool
adam anything to add on that
i mean so one of the things um
that we've been working on is so
like in this paper it's like it's trying
to say like okay so to what degree
um
are the principles of what we understand
about like the natures of like the
hippocampal enter rhino system being
reflected in this simultaneous
localization and mapping problem in
latent slam
um and
some of the other work we're doing is
also going in the reverse direction
of um
you know what can these
principles
of these slam principles use for
autonomous navigation
what can they tell us about uh the brain
functioning as a cybernetic system and
so
one idea in general is that
um each of these operations in addition
to having this
fundamental significance of the of the
basics of being able to move through the
world this you know um
uh
tasks that any you know active
inferential system that's uh
going to survive and repeat and
do what it needs to do has to handle but
um
to what extent
were these same principles repurposed
for
sophisticated inference more generally
and they're actually and
to what degree is sophisticated
inference structured according to uh
slam principles
and so
um
so like
if you're talking about these like loop
closure events like this finding this
highly familiar
state and where you you think you know
where you are by this
convergence of like your trajectory
information and your pose
well this question would be like
um is this a model potentially for
the feeling of insight
or uh discovering of like um
causal accounts
um is this uh
and is this actually a inter and intra
individual source of inter individual
differences
which would be uh fairly fundamental
like how familiar do you think things
are or not
um
how much do you update on accounting or
encountering these highly familiar
situations and so like um
so me personally what i've been
wondering is
so to what a sense like of all the
details um so towards degree
so re-representing the biological
details in terms of the kinds of
descriptions that
tim is giving here
and also though thinking of
cognition more generally as navigation
and so thinking of like each of these
things what are the analogs at the level
of thought
as a kind of navigation through
generalized space
wow awesome
navigation
a lot of interesting work on exploration
exploitation in mind and space hills at
all 2015 and on thinking about
planning and the evolution of planning
as being related to spatial as well as
cognitive foraging it's blue
so it's interesting to think about
cognition as um navigation
like i think about the feeling that i
have when i'm like searching for
a thought a word a name of a person like
it literally feels like a
like you're scrolling through a filing
cabinet like physically looking for
this like piece of information in your
brain and i know that like
different neurons like store different
pieces of information like the jennifer
aniston neuron and and these kinds of
things
so i wonder what um
can you just elaborate maybe a little
bit more on that adam about like
cognition as navigation is it like
literally navigating to find the right
like neuron that goes ding ding ding
ding ding that's the one i wanted
so like
to subject three it could be and that
like
it's like two ways i might think of it
as one um like you were talking earl um
before and you really bring up like
memory palaces
and i think that'll be like one example
of thought as navigation navigation
which is like with this like art of
memory
in terms of like it can be like part of
the way we
um
access and organize
the information we work with when we're
thinking
is through a kind of spatialization
often and actually like to the extent
that we show like really great
virtuosity with memory it's through an
explicit process of spatializing and
navigating through domain
and that gives us like the best purchase
we have on um
you know remembering these building
constructing and accessing these complex
structures
uh but in terms of what you're
describing with like something kind of
like you know jennifer anderson or like
uh neurons are like kind of
finding uh
uh
the things coming to mind there's like
foraging theory and so it's what you
might be foraging for like when you're
like looking for like uh something that
fits it is it's a certain amount of like
familiarity or like some amount of like
you know it could take different forms
like you know some sort of uh yeah
maybe maybe it's a enteroceptive code
and it's like like a visceral feeling of
like
compelling this or maybe it's like a
more like a proprioceptive code and it's
like tension in the body i i don't know
what it might be but this like you're
you're there's some sort of
read you're having
and
are you finding what you're looking for
and so then the idea would be like
you're foraging for it and so you might
spend a little bit of time
in
some area of conceptual space and you're
kind of moving around in there like
trying out different permutations
and then you're like nah i'm not finding
it and then you might do like a
different tech and then move to another
area of semantic or conceptual space and
you're searching around there and so
like in forging theory these would be
called um i believe levy flights and so
there's like something called the
marginal value theorem which is like if
you're trying to be an optimal forager
um
you're trying to like balance expiration
exploitation and so you don't want to
spend too long in a given like patch
if it's not having what you want but you
you don't want to leave a patch
prematurely if it's a good patch to be
exploited and so the idea is like if
you're looking for like
searching for a name or something that
fits it might take the form of this kind
of like generalized foraging but instead
of
you like locomoting through spaces
you're actually spending different
amounts of time in semantic spaces and
then shifting
based on whether you think you're
actually it's like a a juicy patch
and so like with the marginal value
theorem it says like if your current
rate of foraging drops below the
historical return
then you should um
then you should go um
and so this like there might be
different like inductive biases in the
brain that would represent this like
from like the campbell system this might
look like for instance like um
uh the way-by-planet is like you might
get like this um
friction error drops below a certain
amount
um or goes past a certain amount and
then the hippocampal system like ramps
up with a lot of her current activity
it's called like a ripple
and then it resets itself and like
re-tiles the space and like
stimulates cortex like a new like
set of operative policies and
spatializations
might occur
and so like this would be like an
example like a mechanism like the
capital system might have like a
built-in mechanism for like these like
attentional shifts and shifts and these
imaginative shifts when you're doing
foraging it might be reflected also in
like other ways like uh like dopamine so
there's like some thoughts um i think
that like nathaniel dahl will talk about
like
one way of interpreting opponency
between like phasic and tonic dopamine
would be like the tonic would tell you
like what's your average return
basically
and there seems to be like a kind of
functional i don't know if it's not
antagonism but like the more your tonic
is high
the more you're uh
the less impactful any phasic event is
and so it would be kind of like um
if you're
foraging like what would occasionally
shift or not
um you might actually see this like
playing out like in the way
neuromodulators work
and so
i don't know if that like helps a lot
but the idea is like this is the sort of
like
um thinking in terms of forging or
navigation through generalized spaces
as basically being
um
so the reason like you know so i guess
there's like a kind of like uh priory
reason like you would expect it to be
um
generally good which is well doesn't
everything
like
and most of the things we encounter do
indeed exist in spaces and then most
things the way we understand them is by
like spatializing them it's like we
graph them we
do like multi-dimensional scaling we do
different things to try to like
it's just like a way we understand
things
but it also seems like this was probably
both evolutionarily and developmentally
like
this was the original challenge that had
to be solved
where the systems were paying their
weight
and that this would then involve like a
repurposing and a redeploying for
more abstract domains
um so like there's some other like um i
think it's burgess um
has done some good work we're like
finding like for instance like
we might create like a morpho space and
we're like looking like um like they'll
create like these generative like birds
with like different like neck lengths
and you're trying to do like categories
over like what the different kinds of
birds are
and there's like there's evidence that
the way we do the categorization is
we'll create
a
a spatialization of this task structure
and
there's some evidence of the hippocampus
system is we're navigating through that
and dealing with these categories
um i know so that's that was a lot of
rambling but like
i don't know if that
god would
any of that land or yeah lots of it
landed it was very cool thank you okay
one note that we'll i'm sure be
exploring going forward optimal foraging
theory is often put in the context of
utility
which is just the pragmatic component in
active inference in terms of policy
selection so optimal active inference
foraging is like when the epistemic and
the pragmatic gain are being considered
so that's quite interesting and then
also there's as you brought up
individual and collective navigation
so one case is sort of the sovereign
robot
no wi-fi onboard computation alone in
the warehouse
but then in the case of for example an
ant colony where there's stigmargy and
modification of the environment
that might
be possible or even facilitated by
different onboard cognition and
different outsourced or offloaded which
brings us to extended cognitive
discussions but let's return to this
question about going from
this resiliency of navigation that
a biologist
knows exists a roboticist might want to
see
how did you then go to that third space
and actually
have a hierarchical model so here in
figure 2 um or wherever else you suggest
what is happening here and how did this
graphical structure come to be as
opposed to potentially like other
graphical structures that could have
been used
okay so
basically um
let me first maybe explain what all the
variables mean in this in this figure
so
going from the bottom uh to up at the
bottom you have the o's ots
which are basically observations so
these are like the visual inputs what do
you what the robot sees basically
and then we have two
latent variables s and p
where s is basically um an estimation of
um
all the latent vectors that give rise to
the observation so this is it's kind of
a latent space that that that confines
all possible visual observations
and uh p on the other hand is a latent
variable that
has a representation of of your pose
which is then basically
um
in in this case
um your
your xy position and the head direction
and then we go
we have one more which is the aid action
and so that's what i i hinted at
[Music]
previously this is basically your
your proprioception you know
you know what you have been doing uh so
there therefore up until uh the past
the the eighties are also shaded so it
means that you you basically have access
to
uh
what you have been doing it's like the
low level action like move forward to
this philosophy or turn left or right
but then for the future this becomes an
unobserved thing and you basically want
to infer
potential actions you should be doing in
in the future
and then
for the future uh a a number of actions
can be just uh
summarized as pi which is then the
policy so the policy is no more than a
sequence of future actions that you that
you uh that you want to do or that you
intend to do
and then we move up a level in hierarchy
and there
we have uh two more variables one is uh
the location l
and this is then basically kind of a
more coarse-grained um
um
yeah
representation of location where am i
but it's not really uh it's not
necessarily tied to
a metric space it's just like
identifying this is a location
and then
we have uh also an action space at this
level but this is the more uh uh we call
this moves or m
and the move is basically kind of um
moving from one location to another so
locations can just be more coarse grains
like
what you uh
what you define as like a separate
location in in your environment
uh whereas at the lower level the the
the states if you move from one state to
the other it's basically just saying
okay
what would be the next frame of my
camera sensor would be like and so it's
also crucial to know that these two
levels operate on different kind of time
scales so the the lowest level time
scale is basically a very fine
fine grained um action perception loop i
i send the motor commands to the robot
and i read out my camera and this can go
to um
i think we implemented it at like 10
hertz so 10 times per second we get a
new camera frame we finally updated the
motor command
whereas the location is just like um
moving from one location to another can
can take you maybe 10 or or or more time
steps at the lower level
and then of course one of the crucial
bits is then
when when do you
how do you then how do you identify a
location
and so basically how
how it comes to be is that if you you
you you basically observe your uh
your space through the camera images we
infer this abstract state space s and
then we look at what what is the
surprise
of
being in this state versus uh what i
predicted and if this surpasses like a
certain threshold
um so
uh yeah it's so this is uh
it's pretty complex to explain but i'll
do my best so so every time every time
step you get basically a new camera
image and you can calculate like what is
what is the kl divergence between what i
was thinking about the state previously
and how does it that how did it shift
with my new observations and basically
your kind of the bayesian surprise that
you had
from seeing this observation and every
time step we accumulate like this number
and once we surpass a certain threshold
which is kind of a hyper parameter we
just fix it that's something that seems
to work so if you surprise this
threshold you basically say okay
this is now distinct enough from end
time steps before
so it must be something new it must be a
new kind of
location in my neck and then you add
this
thing as a distant distinct location in
your map and you add like a link from
the previous location to this one and
you start and then you continue further
on building the map
and this is how you then kind of create
this more coarse grained um
map of your environment
and um
and you can then um reason like how
should i move from this location to
another and you then can you can
basically use your
your previously visit locations and and
moves to kind of i have a model of
how can i move in this space but at the
more of course great level moving from
one uh location to another and it also
means that by by using this surprise on
infertility in space that that we infer
from from visual input
it means that it it's not not every edge
has the same distance in real space
necessarily so if you're if you're the
robot is traversing
a white hallway where the the the the
walls are perfectly white and everything
that everything's the same
then it will take a long time for this
threshold to be reached and it will only
at
uh larger distances make a new node
because everything looks the same anyway
so there's no extra information that i
need to put in the map but if you then
suddenly
see a door for example then you suddenly
reach your threshold and you add a new
location in your map and so it's
basically the locations in the map are
basically defined of uh on
what is the information i got by looking
at this thing rather than um how much
meters did i traverse uh in in this in
this time and it makes it a really
interesting way of of representing maps
because it's more like how much
information uh
is there in this particular location
rather than uh
which xy locat position is is here
does it make sense
yeah
and
it feels to map onto the distinction
between like kronos and kairos
like in this analogy here kronos is the
the chronometer it's the watch time it's
the geometry it's the xy grid it's one
meter and then kairos is like the
timeliness of action and the time it
takes to complete an action
and then something being like boring
that's going through a low information
hallway
in the cognitive foraging it's like are
we there yet driving through this
featureless landscape where the salience
is low because my predictions are
basically being
um met almost too well
and there's a lot of other
ways to go with it um
adam anything to add and also again i'm
just kind of curious like what is the
space of the possible graphical
structures do you think that this is the
only or the sort of
grandfather graphical model for
hierarchical navigation like how do we
go from imagining this tactics and
strategy multi-level model to a
graphical model that we believe will be
consistent with active inference and
amenable to message passing
and maybe
to add on on this last question um
i think kristen has a
has a paper on deep temporal
article models where he basically lays
out more generic so like the if you're
looking at the ultimate generic
hierarchical model you'll find it there
where it's basically just an aggregation
of
states
that give rise to observations
that
go from one state to another given an
option
and then you can add that level on top
and level on top and you can keep on
adding levels
and that's kind of the prototypical
hierarchical model i would say um
and what you see here is kind of
particular instantiation where we
took um some uh domain knowledge like
okay for navigation what would be
sensible levels to think about and what
would these uh latent states then what
should they represent and then of course
uh
you easily end up like okay
at the lowest level i i need to have
some state that represents my camera
images and at the higher level uh i want
to have some locations in the map um
and
how do they then relate okay i i
probably also want to have this the spot
integration so maybe i i need to have a
special
special first class citizens here in in
the form of my pose
and that's how you basically build up
the model from first looking at this
prototypical hierarchical model
then looking at yeah but in my case what
do i think is sensible what could these
things mean
and then try to figure out like okay
um
at this at this stage we kind of
converge on the one hand from
top down like does the math work out to
bottom up does this match match with my
implementation and then at some point we
converge to this basically
so the high road and the low road they
they do lead to rome after all
exactly
adam what would you add in there
um
well first of all uh
i i love that metaphor just now another
thing i would add
is um
so like you know on my ends like i'm
trying to use this as like
um
abstractions for understanding you know
aspects of like brain functioning so
let's say we're talking about these um
um
you know this top level
um this is one way of interpreting like
uh you know hippocampal place cells
um
and and the these um
whether you create a new node or not
based on what threshold of familiarity
or surprise
um this would potentially be like an
example i think
of
um it's an extremely uh
powerful source of individual
differences
like um maybe you could think of this in
terms of like uh piagetian like
assimilation or accommodation but you
could see like if your thresholds are
too low or too high
you can end up representing a domain
in ways with um
there are other
um
you can get false you can get things
that are like excessively granular or
insufficiently granular to represent the
domain and you can get different types
of errors associated with it and so like
this for instance could define um
even things like more like um
some people will talk like autism to
schizophrenia spectrums and so they said
there could be like kind of underlying
predispositions for this
it might actually be
i think that's an oversimplification but
it you could think of
these thresholds as
some cognitive spectrums might just fall
out of them as you get different types
of minds if you have like a more
granular
like an overly inclusive or an underly
inclusive category structure
but some other things like just drawing
on this would be like if we're talking
about
this um
you know lower level and if we're
thinking of like these um like internal
grid cells as you know what not quite
being
well the pose here aren't quite red
cells but
this idea of like
this um
mapping
of
your
um
what your body position is and where
you're oriented
and then having this conjoined with
what's
in your visual field and then using
these sources of information
uh to mutually constrain each other and
using where you are in space
um
and these all being necessary like for
instance this seems to be you know
fundamentally what was needed to get the
robots to work and we have not so
dissimilar sensors and effectors
and so well one thought is um
you know
i think it's um
um
dubai has um just messed up his name
but um
he has this interesting here uh paper
and like default mode system as um it's
called a dark control and thinking of it
as doing like tree search
but
um
to loop it around
this pose information it's possible that
some of the posterior nodes of the dmn
are actually helping to encode this
information
um
like if you go like to the parietal
portions that actually might be where is
my body where is it reflected and then
if we're going like to these midline
portions of it um
you know
what's in my visual field or what am i
imagining
and then if you want to go for like this
future part that might be like the
anterior portions
um so like the dmn or the
the
dorsal medial prefrontal cortex may be
coupling with the hippocam the anterior
hippocampus but
basically it would seem that like the
stream
these core aspects of the model might be
ways of functionally understanding
the core aspects of
an agent architecture
used for um mental stimulation
uh
that
there seems to be a striking amount of
um convergence between
the things that um people like tim
identifying is just like what's
necessary how do we solve a problem
and the features of normal organization
uh that would be these
defaults or
canonical processes that you just you're
you're seeing it as a
as really just
fundamental like you know
we call it the default focus and it's
active all the time what's it doing
um maybe part of what it's doing is it's
allowing us to do
um this kind of navigation through
space and time uh
yeah so those are some thoughts
navigation through space and time
in the sort of territory
sense would be clock time and metric
space what is your x y z t
and then navigation through mental space
and time
might have some resonances or analogies
but it's not a piece of grid paper
so what is it and how does it
um become realized through
ecology evolution and development so
awesome points thank you
real quickly in terms of the time issue
it seems like there's these multiple
ways that time comes in it's like one
sense of like the sense of time as you
might be doing like accumulation based
on like um the the frequency with which
you're having like meaningful
informational events um like bud craig
calls it these like global emotional
moments
um but
and and neil and others have some i
think with murray shanahan have some
interesting models like the sense of
time
in terms of like the amount of like uh
information flux through your sensors
but then there's like another kind of
time that might actually involve like
overt spatialization of a trajectory and
you might be using something like path
integration in terms of like how
you're doing some types of duration
estimation
not by necessarily just like
accumulating like
like a sense of accumulation but some of
it might be like where am i and
navigating through a timeline and i
think you'll see this reflected in like
the way people talk and we could like
dismiss this and say like oh that's just
mere metaphor no i i think that that
that metaphor is how we're actually
constructing some sense of time which
actually gives us like
forms of control that we would not have
otherwise were we not able to actually
extend our minds metaphorically in that
way
and
then be able to basically navigate
through spatialized time to keep track
of some longer time sequences
if we want to plan with respect to them
awesome thank you stephen
hello a great seal um yeah i was curious
um in terms of time well one of the
things is do you think time is
um or this process is distributed around
different parts of
the sensorum uh processing because
different sensors have different
speeds or different rates or different
abilities
um and then the other thing coming back
to time as well is people can be going
through time
they can be like
or they can
be time can come towards them
or time can be sort of developing around
them which often happens in asian
cultures it's a time is seen more as a
something that's around them so i'm
curious like how these these ideas of
temporality might might link to
the ways that we imagine ourselves with
our sensorium
i mean if it is indeed the case that
some forms of
the spatialization of
if it is the case of spatializing time
um that's happening both
um
in some cases through some some fairly
um abstract
metaphorical and linguistic instructions
then this would um
imply that you should be able to get
meaningful um cultural differences
based on these shared constructions
and maybe even some like quasi-like
warfare effects where like linguistic
modifications could actually
change the way people are seeing
themselves and others
in relation to time with some fairly
significant consequences
so
um
our word warfarin affects the
jargon of just like um you know the idea
that the um our thought is constrained
in some meaningful way by the uh
constraints and affordances of our
language our constraints importances on
the way we think
there's like stronger and weaker
versions of that hypothesis
thank you blue
so it's interesting because we've been
talking about um like spatial maps and
spatial context like spatial
representation navigating through space
i i have been thinking a lot about um
semantic navigation also like when we're
looking through
looking for a thought um when we're
looking for
um we're navigating foraging for
information or you know in these context
rich domains and and i just wonder um
what
like is the semantic navigation
related to linked to
um like is there overlap in the brain
and the way that we process semantic
orientation and representation and
space
also so i'm just curious
hashtag maps of meaning
yeah maybe uh
i can uh i can respond on this
from from my perspective
and then i'll probably have to leave you
guys
um but so i think one of the most
important things at least to me
uh of
how this this whole endeavor of
constructing this
uh and and doing this together with adam
is that
we basically we start off with uh
it's robot navigation which is
from a roboticist perspective is really
like
about x and y position and about times
and seconds
but what we do here is we by by creating
this model we basically get rid of
this
close tie of
being um grounded in in seconds and
meters basically i think this is one of
the most crucial um aspects of of our
model because it's it shows that well on
the one hand i think we all agree that
we don't get born measuring time in
seconds and measuring
space in meters
so
we actually get at least the framework
that also gets rid of these these
metrics
and just
learns to navigate
in this more abstract space
and if we can get it to work for for
navigation
per se
moving through actual physical space
then i'm pretty sure that we can also
extend them all further to navigate
any abstract space because in the end
these once we are at the
once we get the level above are our
sensory inputs then everything is in our
case just a learned latent thing
basically so if we can if we can make
this work for physical navigation and i
think we are already a
a big step closer to to making it work
for for any navigation then indeed we
come to the realm of like okay i
i have lots of memories these are tied
together somehow because how how these
memories just came to be
can i now navigate the space towards the
memory that i'm looking for
or if you are solving
a math problem how do you navigate the
space of math equations to get the
solution for this thing i i think
once we get rid of um
the the the the the
the time and space that that are so
tight for your your sensorium and
move towards the more abstract space and
be able to navigate that
this is this is the crucial the crucial
bit here i i would say
and so with that i i i'd like to thank
you for for the discussion till now i
i'll try to be there next week as well
and
and enjoy the discussion further
thank you tim
cool very interesting and and uh also
speaking to that
cultural basis
there was the inch foot
pound paradigm
and that has in certain places also
coexisted or
been complementary or contradictory with
the centimeters grams
second based upon something different
and what would happen if a larva was
born and the little one the second was
like what we call three seconds
is that just a more chill larva because
every
one of its moments is taking a few more
heartbeats it can actually take a breath
per little one
so there's a lot that we probably don't
even know how much we don't know
until we're in feedback with these
models
that both
fully realize not just in the equations
but in the actual robotics
grounding us in those actual
observations of red green blue pixel
intensities which is like when adam was
saying that robotics are are an
empirical platform to be studying the
nature of cognition and brain and mind
and then
here
is where we move into
a different space and time
and so that is
an excellent point by tim
stephen
yeah so following on from what you're
saying daniel is um
we i know tim just mentioned about you
know have the abstracted ideas
but there's also maybe the grounded you
mentioned grounded
ways of knowing so
it might be that the future will
abstract out what we think
it might be and then there may be ways
where we feel what's right what feels so
you hit a door
and you feel there's an information
affordance
and it can ground
so i was wondering how much
that can
um that supports not needing to have
the metrics like you say and maybe the
metrics that we've created like the
second
are partly because they're at that kind
of sweet spot or somehow close to a
speech sweet spot of what sort of makes
sense you know someone had to decide on
a foot or a hand you know so
was it the small person's hand was the
big person's hand and they sort of said
well what about john
and maybe he was the king i don't know
but um but it got decided somehow so i
think this is a a good question about
grounding versus abstraction i don't
know what uh
what the thoughts are on that
yes
this higher level in a purely metric
model it could be like well on the
bottom level we're dealing with
centimeters
and 100 milliseconds
frames and the coarse graining is at the
level of 100 times the spatial distance
and 100 times the temporal distance
what this model is doing is something
different and i think that is again this
biological inspiration which is that
what is happening in the level that the
action perception loop
is nested within
is not just a a bigger version
[Music]
well it both is and isn't because it has
some
resonance graphical structures
that support the composability and the
tractability of active models
yet also it's doing something that's
categorically different which is
navigating in a more topological
space rather than the more geometric
space down the bottom what are you um
thinking about adam
um
it seems like the
well i guess one is i suspect
it is no coincidence that
seconds
are about the time
extent that they are
and that we have like the metric units
we use like a foot
or a meter or a yard
in terms of like
in terms of grounding and in terms of
connection to affordance so like a
second for maybe you know
a relation to certain
maybe like
heart rate or certain like biophysical
pattern generators or like the scope of
working memory being
an iconic memory being stable on
different
scales
or like a yard or a meter like the
basically on the reach that you have of
your arm like like perry personal space
and like
uh
a field of affordances around your body
where it's particularly concentrated
um
and so
you know these are ways in which like
for instance like the granularity
of our
modeling would be influenced by language
or their language would reflect it and
maybe
um to different extents influence it but
you would have like this other kind of
granularity of space
that might be different for different
species but also within a species and
with an individual like for instance
like these like tilings
of
um
so like
the campus system will like lay out
these like tilings of space
for a task domain and they'll have like
a a kind of
they'll be refreshed like maybe it looks
like like every three seconds or so
but if you're in like a big space
um
but this tiling will actually affect of
hexagonal
arrays or effects just like hexagonal
tongue it'll fill whatever space it's in
and it'll have different levels of
granularity
and so if you're in like a big space
it's going to necessarily be less
granular and if you're in a small space
it'll be uh probably be more granular
but there's other things that influence
the granularity also like um
uh
there's like brain stem locomotor nuclei
they're like detecting how fast are you
moving and then this will influence the
granularity of like your
tiling of space
and so
that's um it's like some of it um
you know
some of the of this uh what is relevant
uh some of this this
uh our greening of a domain some of it
will be reflected by like these uh
basically innate like
by um architectural inductive biases and
some of them will be more like
socioculturally constructed
um
one thing just uh we're moving on is i
thought i like how um uh tim you know as
he left like that that was that was one
uh hell of a mic drop because you know
the thing is like basically yeah so he's
already solved like in terms of kinds of
grounding
like not only is this like potentially a
way of having
an architecture capable of navigating
conceptual domains and abstractions
basically what bengio calls like system
2ai
or what some would call like strong ai
but it's also grounding in that it
actually works as a control system for
an embodied embedded agent and so now
you might have a single system capable
of both giving you symbol grounding by
allowing something to be in the world
alongside other agents
and have actual
actual semantics
um in terms of pointing to things in the
world like you can have like a semantic
network um
just like symbols pointing at symbols
but ultimately these such a system would
allow you to ground out your semantic
network
in things in the world and shared
symbols
and so um i mean ultimately this is a
path to you know who knows how far um
you know anyone working on it today gets
but this is ultimately a path to agi
built
that takes on an activist principles of
what you would need to do so
which is more than a little exciting i
think
oh i'm starting to see why people are
interested in this
excellent point about the symbolic
semantics and logic and how that
connects to the inactive insight the
pragmatic turn
ecological psychology biosemiosis like
all of these features that get left
on the cutting block if we take a
computational linguistics approach only
and uh computational linguistics plus
the mouth movement already one has
incorporated
that pragmatic turn and that embodiment
element and that's quite a different
model than just the substrate
independent symbol
manipulator
stephen yeah i think it's exciting
indeed because it can open up a lot of
i'm really interested in mental space
psychology and perry personal space and
working with space as an instrument and
uh well i'm more than interested in it
that's my main focus
in in many ways and um
but what's really been the challenge is
um
giving it a plausible bridge right back
because they're working primarily you're
looking at what action policies are
and what has been enacted
um and it's very hard to go back to
observations because you're coming from
the other direction so
i think it'd be really interesting to
see what this robot whether you could
actually see well what kind of robot is
this robot
what's it like what kind of
story patterning gets triggered by this
robot and maybe if i
it grew up with a slightly heavier
wheel on one side or something it has a
slightly different
character you know so i mean i wonder if
there's a kind of an actual
uh a way that the action policies
themselves start to encode
a certain personality
based on
the physicality and
sensorim that get weighted
i mean that would be like in terms of
this like generalization of um slam
principles
as like a way of understanding cognition
more generally i think that would be
like a great test case and that like
those are the kinds of hypotheses you
would look for
um
i think you're if your wheel is like
weighted more heavily on one side or the
other
that could have all sorts of things like
for instance like
um like
what
tim was describing like this node
creation
where it's not just a function of like a
metrics but on
information
and
the
and so this creates like a
a distorted space but but an adaptively
distorted space you would expect usually
because multiple forms of value are
influencing the granularity of this um
instead of space like necessarily it's
like a map it's like space is a graph
but but a graph being shaped by multiple
kinds of value
and so you would expect things like like
that kind of wheel asymmetry you're
talking about to result
in different kinds of graft spaces and
this could then potentially have some
transfer
um more generally
across more than just physical spaces in
theory
um
also you know coming back to that
granularity issue like let's say like um
the way you move through the world is
quicker or slower
that itself then might have transferred
not just to well how is it that i'm
representing the space i'm physically
moving through but that then could get
reflected in cognitive styles in terms
of like the way you re you relate to
like semantic spaces in terms of the way
you you're going to forage through them
um what you consider to be um near or
far connections so like this is the kind
of like
and that would be like a whole research
program
which would be
um but using this as like a source of
bridging principles of like so some
connection between embodied experience
and then more abstract thinking well
maybe this is a source of some of the
ways in which concrete and body
experiences go on to
shape
um
basically fought on a more abstract
level as well
very
interesting and especially when we think
about the mental action
papers that we've read like live stream
number 25 with xanthed smith at all
about metacognition as mental action
and so
in this two-level robotics case
we're talking about the sort of
lower level motion
and then the higher level navigation of
locations where we can say i want to go
to the post office and then the grocery
store but then we have this more
tactical taking a step
time scale that's a lot faster
if this bottom layer is
based upon cognition and perception also
this higher level is not just navigation
in
the warehouse that's actually like where
do i want to be in my regime of
attention or what would i like to be
considering from a metacognitive
perspective how do i navigate to a place
where i prefer what's healthy for me so
there's all kinds of other questions
about navigation in parameter spaces
that are not just like
topologically the cousin of the
warehouse space but truly
in the mental space fully um blue and
then stephen
so since we brought up hierarchical um
here in the paper it looks like and i
mean i can hold this for tim adam too if
you don't feel like comfortable talking
about it but maybe maybe you're you're
good um in the hierarchical space
it seems that it's just a core screening
like in this paper right so like you
know the the higher level is just like a
coarse grained version of what happens
at the lower level
and it's easy to see how that takes
place or takes shape in
like a topographical way um
it doesn't leave a lot of room for
emergence and i wonder like if we jump
to thinking about a semantic space
um you know we have words we've got the
relationships with words to each other
proximity you know how close do you
expect to find you know there to was or
or whatever so so how how linked are the
words together in a semantic space but i
wonder if you know you can go into topic
modeling and that gives you like a kind
of a core screening
but but like is there more room for
emergence in that kind of
space maybe
um or like what other like how do you i
don't know how how would you
just allow
for emergent things to come through in
this kind of hierarchical modeling or
mapping
i think um when
tim comes back um it could be worth it
for him to go into more detail
on the
parameters that go into
uh
node creation or not
because i feel like
to the extent that you're getting
some flexibility and ways of
understanding like emergence
that would be your your models of
emergence and or whether that would be
like where
you would basically create um
this corresponding ontology of different
levels of granularity
what um
what constitutes like an occasion for
core screening of what kinds
um
it seems like
the node creation would be where your
your assumptions about that
of what kinds of emergency might be
dealing with
um
that's where it would come into this
kind of model
um is it rich enough
uh to account for like oh i i wouldn't
quite say that um
in terms of like you know all the
different forms of emergency you can get
um so some of it you know
but that is for but for um by enough i
mean you know enough to be you know a
full on general intelligence but
um
but but i do think there is room for
some
some flexibility there um at that
parametrization of of tim's model but
he would explain it better than i would
i'll i'll make a comment and then ask a
question in the chat and then also see
stephen so um it was mentioned that uh
there is the embodiment of certain prior
information in the continuous attractor
network like if my position is this and
i move forward then that is putting me
into this different position in the can
and um
blue asked about topic modeling in
semantic spaces so that territory is
different so the maps should be
appropriately different and so we could
say for example
like
california is nested within the united
states
that is not violating any geographical
priors
but um what about a paper that's
interdisciplinary
that might be at the intersection of two
different topics or depending on how
those topic models are generated
one could think of every paper as
existing across 100 different topics to
different quantitative amounts and so it
actually does bring us to this question
which sid has asked which is
we're hearing
a lot in in the paper in the natural
speech and so on
different
complementarities
lower and higher
so here where the lower model is the
finer scale and the the red i'm trying
not to mix metaphors but lower and
higher
is sometimes used with inner and outer
or finer and coarser coarse graining
more specific more general so
what is that
restaurant
where those are the dishes
how could it something be above or below
and you get it but it could also be more
like a kernel and more like the fruit
and you get it and it could be more like
sand or more like gravel and you would
get it
what does that mean or say
we'll think and then allow adam to speak
first
i think that's a deep and complex
question
um
and there's a couple levels or a couple
of entry points there but
um one thing is like you mentioned like
inner and outer is another way of
describing it's supposed to higher and
lower and there's there's a
i think connection between this arc this
leighton stem architecture
and like um
and meta learning where you're
um having like a more fine-grained
process for like
that's more task specific and for like
adaptive five-grain couplings but then
you nest that
rather you create like an outer loop
which is like a slower aggregation
process that's coarser but then allows
for sharing of information across
episodes
and so it's a kind of like
so this is basically a kind of metal
learning system
and giving you this divide and conquer
approach of like levels of granularity
um
i don't think
anyone quite knows um yet
what the significance of this is but one
interesting thing about the grid cells
is they seem to have
a multi-scale hierarchy in their
organization
in terms of there's this axis
i believe is as you go
within enter rhino cortex as you go like
more um
uh
dorsal to ventral or more superior to
inferior
it you'll get these like
discrete cut-offs
of um
potentially implying some kind of
um harmonic nesting of scales maybe even
coupling with like multi-scale like
synchronous
dynamics and cortex unclear
um but there does seem to be these like
multiple scales reflected
in the or in grid skills in internal
crystals having different levels of
granularity of their spatial
representations
and the the thing that's interesting i
i'm curious about is like one of the
or one thing i'm curious about is like
to what degree for instance
do different neuromodulator systems like
some of the ways in which like
they could be understood in terms of
like them having their functions is
maybe like influencing which granularity
is most
um present like moving into like now
we're in a situation of like attending
to like the fine granules and or this is
a situation where we're going to really
go course and just ignore those details
and that some neuromodulatory systems
there um
and their effects on like neurodynamics
might actually be best explained might
be well explained in terms of this like
adaptive changing of the granularity
very
cool and we see that in teamwork where
sometimes it's time to control paste
and just fill out the spreadsheet other
times it's time to add a column to the
spreadsheet other times there are this
open-endedness to the task and including
the
local objectives and also even broader
mission and one's own relationship to
the team in the project so
um
perhaps if there's a similar biological
substrate
then it would stand to reason that there
could be multiple
representations that are emitted from
some kind of common generative model
stephen
uh um like the cop thought before i
forget um
so one thing that i'm actually really
interested in is exploring these slam
principles
in the insect case because they have
like um analogous and potentially
largely homologous systems with the
central complex
and
i feel like that's a like um an area
like i'm looking to look into next is
like to really understand these things
not just looking at the mammal case but
i look at the insect case with the
central complex and see the similarities
and differences you know what what
special adaptations were there um
what what to what are the functions
realized by similar means or different
means but
this um in terms of like a way of
understanding things like like that
neuromodulator hypothesis of like
influencing like the granularity of
spatial modeling
it's possible although i wouldn't you
know necessarily um
that on that i'm based on conversations
with you david but like um
it's possible that then you're getting
like extensive homology and common
significances for things like flexible
influencing the granularity of the
forging parameters it's possible those
are con like remarkably conserved and
that you might actually see them
that being said like you also were
alluding to though the slam instance is
different than insects in that this is a
this is a multi-slam
um in general there's a lot of
multi-stem happening you know
invertebrates also but i think not to
the same degree and that so you might
expect some potentially substantial
differences there as a result of
the slam problem being having that
additional weights additional set of
challenges and
uh uh sources of information it can
leverage
i can't wait for solitary wasp slam
and you social colony slam
stephen
from what i'm hearing you could you
could correlate these multi slams to
regimes of attention in many ways
because
that that could dictate the nature of
these granularities and where they are
in the space and the place in the body
so
um because
we often assume i think when blue is
saying they're about
there's there's
inner outer and the some of those are
also false assumptions that that rolls
out over everything
that we should so in the sense that
inner
is
purer and higher is purer but often
that might depend on the multi slam
that's being dunked at the time
yeah like um one note then blue like
coarser and finer slower and faster so
one interpretation would be that the
slower time scale is the coarser
graining
in the sense that it's like seconds not
milliseconds and the finer is the faster
but there's also maybe an interpretation
where actually the if you're clicking up
mile by mile instead of foot by foot
that is actually moving faster and it's
coarser and if you're counting grains of
sand at a time it's finer and slower so
i think even sometimes the direction
that one interprets
is not there but it doesn't remove the
dialectical nature or the intermodal
nature but the the way that um is it
going to be like um
[Music]
a sugar with all the ohs pointing down
or all the o h is pointing up or some
blend has to go one way or the other but
maybe it doesn't have to be any one
specific way
blue
so
i am wondering and this is also
interesting in terms of the insights
case
if there's some kind of um
maybe like a generic
pre-installed like
readily adaptable coarse-grained version
of a place cell like that's just
kind of there is like a generic
representation so like a perfect example
i mean when you're thinking about core
screening like a map at a location like
you know where everything is in your
house like you know where your bathroom
is and you know where all the things are
but you know when you travel you have an
expectation even if you've never been to
the hotel before you have the
expectation of what the elevator is
going to sound like how the carpet all
looks the same with that funky weird
pattern and the hallways twist and turn
and
like when you get into the hotel room
there's going to be a bathroom and
there's going to be a window and there's
going to be a bed and a tv and a remote
so you have this like
pre generic
supposition of how the hotel is going to
look does that live in a place cell
somewhere that just like morphs into oh
the bathroom's here and the light's here
so that you're not stumbling around in
the middle of the night like and
similarly like there's all kinds of when
you go out hiking you know you expect
there to be trees and rocks and and
stuff outside and so do you just like
mash your map onto like some
pre-existing generic
place holder a place cell placeholder
it's interesting to think about
it's like a prior for the abstract space
it's a prior distribution over hotel
rooms which is totally uncultured and
totally based upon experience and then
either one is surprised or not just as
with when any other
prior meets
sense
um adam what do you think it then steve
i mean these are um
details that are definitely like
half or beyond the edge of anything
um i or maybe anyone knows but the
um
i guess you said like these
how many different
so one way that these um place fields
are sometimes modeled
is in terms of like these like chained
attractors
and so like within the hippocampus
system like you can get like this highly
recurrent activity
especially in some of the subfields
and
you can set up like this set of um
these densities of
um
recurrent activity and then you could
have like information kind of moving
between them as a like predictive map
not just of like
not just like here's the things but um
you know people debate how best things
like gershman talks about success
representations but that there's a
transition structure
of which attractor will act which of the
places will activate first in the
sequence
and
and so i guess the question the question
i'm wondering is so like you know you're
encountering like a new scene and you're
like laying down like a set of landmarks
or a tiling of space
like
to what degree
is this information encoded in
um in what circumstances and to what
degree is it
encoded in like the local connectivity
within the campus system and whether
you're getting like this set of schemas
that you're gonna like draw up like the
most similar one based on
some like degree of similarity will
cause like one attractor network to get
pulled up over another and now this is
the talent you're working within and
this is like
the policies for the the policy set
you're likely to be pulling from and
this is your framing of the domain
um
or to what degree is it relying more
heavily
on like the moments of moments um like
cortical dynamics and like the mental
simulation that might be happening and
like to which
extent like is it constrained
by the history of plasticity within the
hippocampus what schemas are going to be
operative
um and to what degree is it more of a
negotiation
where it's going to be more ad hoc
more determined by the momentum
contingencies and this funneling through
the whole
like
cortical virtual reality machinery or
everyone think of it
um
and to what degree is this
there's not one answer this varies both
across within individuals
that this is actually like
a core aspect of cybernetic functioning
is actually
leaning more heavily on the priors or
the current of
established
um over more than more learning efforts
are leaning more on like the
situationally specific factors like how
much do you shoehorn what's going on
into your existing schemas how much do
you simulate how much do you accommodate
and that this being potentially like a
flexible parameter
and maybe some of that flexibility is
like is
like baked into the logic of
neuromodulators like
actually flexibly influencing this
uh unclear but like yeah certainly uh
very very edge of anything but it's it's
very much like
part of the excitement for me is like
wondering like
is this like
um
does this provide like like like a
functional an algorithmic significance
for like
this like otherwise like just mess of
like biological details like do some of
them have like elegant cybernetic
understandings
by virtue of like
thinking of these kinds of questions
can i just respond really quickly yes
please blue um
so
that made me think a whole bunch about
like maybe we don't need a map a place
cell for each individual hotel room but
it's like a node when we were discussing
nodes earlier like a coarse grained just
an attractor space like dump all of the
hotel room maps into this little nodule
so that when you get to a hotel room
it's all the same
thing like it's oh okay i've been here
before even if you've never been to that
kind of place and and that would kind of
explain things like deja vu like when
you get to a place like i've been here
before when did i come here like when
you're driving down the street didn't i
just drive down this street
you it just lumped over there into that
little attractor
mesh node that's not necessarily a
specific
place but just like a squishy ball of
similar places
and also i really love how we spoke
about some of these things
adam and your collaboration with colin
de young cybernetic big five
in live stream number 13 i think at the
beginning of 2021
and now we're revisiting
same but different more things change
the more they stay the same and this
idea of like modulatory features of
cybernetic systems as being important
for variation within and among
individuals is just such an essential
point and it's so true that
a lot of the details are yet to be
resolved stephen
yeah you could go a bit further still
because
what if you don't have maps put to one
side but there's action policies
and i've actually been interested in how
much this is feasible but action
policies that recapitulate something
like a map
so like
by an embodiment by an inactive chain of
or initiation of some actions at
different scales it basically
recapitulates some sort of
nascent
starting point so you don't have to have
any representations there and like when
the door is
engaged
the set of actions
that that
that creates could open up
an effectively a map um so i don't know
how much between
i mean i know in this model it does
start to create a network of attractors
but i'm wondering whether how much
things could
be sparked off from
engaging a particular affordance a
particular meaningfulness in something
um
i mean
there's actually
like a live debate um about like
the extent to which
so like tolman initially was talking
about the hippocampal cognitive map
and part of the reason people like to
talk about maps is because of the um
flexibility they give you
in terms of
um if you
um like the map serves as a generative
model and that it like it it gives you
like a
um
i can flexibly access it to generate
trajectories but you can do that with a
well-structured graph also but there's
like a spectrum of interpretations of
people thinking
that you're dealing with more things
that are more map-like
and things that are more
um
context-specific and graph like
and and flexible and more dynamically
constructed and
it seems like you know um
like
it's kind of a pop-up but in general i'm
like i always like take every debate and
i'm like you're probably both right and
so it's like
you want like for the sake of i guess
maybe stability
or for the sake of
um potentially greater transfer
of understandings and
inferential power across episodes you
might want something more map like
but if you go to map like you're losing
like the ability to deal like the
nuances of like specific contexts
and so
um
you know so this again this might be
like different perspectives on the same
thing that that tend to converge with
trade-offs like you could have
more context-sensitive or more um
situationally invariant representations
and and these could reflect cognitive
styles and and maybe like fundamental
axes of variation for cognition and
sense-making
um
yeah the
one thing that's uh
in terms of like cybernetics uh danielle
pointed out like earlier like you know
like jordan peterson like part of like
it's actually interesting that um maps
of meeting um peterson's book was
actually heavily informed by
um jacques pancep's affective
neuroscience
and ecological models more generally
like based on things like animal
foraging so i actually think that's
where jordan peterson got that rhetoric
about maps is actually from doing a kind
of
affective neuroscience perspective
grounded um in
the this ecological perspective of
forging animals
and so
yeah i think that's actually where that
came from
yes
very nice and and i think i agree we may
have even
explored as such
in in one paper reimagining maps that i
wrote with rj and a colleague mikel
we learned about this historical
distinction between archival maps and
itinerary maps and today we just think
about maps as being like one more lumpy
category but there's many differences
between the map that actually is like a
multi-map
or mega map and holds a lot of
information potentially in a metric way
versus the itinerary map head straight
until you see the two big trees then
you're going to want to take a left that
type of more conversational or casual or
navigable map that is highly contextual
and with current map systems that's one
of the challenges because we have that
mega map
it's downloadable but it's not going to
fit on your phone
so what is the
projection that's contextual and
situational that's actually going to
enable effective action
that is also going to be perceived as
map like by the user
um
yes blue
so this is like a personal attack in
question
so anybody who spent any kind of time
with daniel knows that he's constantly
drawing or writing or or writing things
down like all the time taking notes
taking notes taking notes and i i wonder
like can you take your notes as like a
mental map of where you were at that
time that you were making that drawing
like does it like
recapitulate your
conversations that you were having the
ideas that were running through your
head like can you use these drawings
that you're always doing as like a kind
of conversational like mental space map
if anything it's the opposite
i just leave the thought behind and if
we look at this i think okay something
happened by which we wrote this down it
would be awesome if there was
many people with their regime of
attention on taking live notes i know
that's not an approach for everybody but
then we could all look at that shared
pheromone distribution
and then make it new again and maybe we
remember our exact previous thought
though that's impossible or unlikely but
instead we can make the
relationship with the material and with
those notes like new again
stephen
yes maybe a little harder to categorize
with language but
in a way it's the traces of
your action policies
even if it was capturing
the interpretation so one thing i'm very
interested in is how we if we realign
things to action
um because
we we've kind of been enculturated to
think it's all about thoughts and
feelings right and
because action active inference puts it
in this other domain
what does that mean
and how do we talk about active
inference when we're cult enculturated
to think through other
natural ways of using english i'm
finding that a big challenge myself but
i think so as you're laying down those
traces
are you showing your action policies of
how to
record something
rather than your thoughts
if that makes sense
um and is your thoughts always slightly
hidden
yeah great question just like we were
thinking about earlier with a sort of
substrate implicit agnostic ignored
linguistic symbolic models
like a turing tape it has infinite space
and it can just make infinite grammar
and so that sort of purely symbolic
approach to language
and then its relationship to thought and
experience is one question but when we
think about finite actual sequences of
language use and deployment as action
either keyboard typing or assisted
typing technology
or speaking as also a motor action
it totally changes the game because
we're not just in this forest of
infinite plausible grammars but rather
one realized and preferred action
sequence and then of course thoughts are
unobserved but the actions are not and
there's that's the whole
quantum reference frame and shared
generative model and rhetorical nature
narrative nature of cognition and so
indeed the the action
insight i think is going to be something
that we'll keep returning to
um
we'll have a final
closing the plane or whatever
and um
i'll also just
give a little preview
which is that next week
we're going to be having a guest stream
with adam
so
if it relates at all adam how does it
relate
what is the guest stream going to be
about and then um
perhaps in your absence what would be
exciting to discuss in 42.2
um
oh you're right there is a guest stream
um a quick thought though uh
so like blue you were suggesting like
daniel's notes could serve almost like a
kind of memory palace
and and
accessible map and then dana you're
saying it's more like a stigmatistic um
mechanism for coordination like with
pointing and cueing
and that's interesting
i wonder if like when people are reading
books like the ability to like use the
book as a like as a map slash palace
like gives you better retention than
something like a kindle
like the book is like a physical object
anyways so um oh yeah uh
free will and so because for next week
uh i would say that basically
so so my like over hypothesis is that
like
all of the details or other
that many of the details
that tim is using for these systems will
end up being
relevant
as abstract interpretations
of the core
um
parameters of us as active inferential
cybernetic systems
both are with respect to basically the
the basics of it lets us be in the world
in a embodied way as uh
as uh
living
living robots
but um
also in terms of their extension to um
high level cognition scaling active
inference to more complex domains
and it's like in general like um
you know i'm i'm trying to understand
you know with
limited success as many details as i can
of tim's work because i i think it's
just some of the most promising sources
of like
constraints we have on inference and
interpretations and sources of
hypotheses so
basically whatever details tim is going
to get into i think you'll be
well well worthwhile to try to grock
those and
that's what i'm that's what i'm doing
um
in terms of next week
so
some of this is relevant and that um
the basic idea would be that
um
these uh le bay phenomenon these studies
in which people are seeing these
slowly building potentials leading up to
action that have predictive information
but where they peak
um
in advance of people claiming that they
have decided to take actions and where
these studies are interpreted as
evidence that people don't have free
will we can get into
you know all sorts of
uh conversations about you know how we
what makes how it makes sense to think
free will in different ways whatever
makes sense to talk about it all
but that these studies are usually
interpreted as saying that your
um
consciously experienced mental states
cannot enter causal streams leading to
action
and so what i'm suggesting is that it's
not the case and that there's multiple
ways in which your subjective states are
meaningfully causal
if we think of what's leading up to
something like deciding to move your
hand in like a bad experiment
if that is reflecting a buildup of model
evidence over your proprioceptive pose
or of you deciding to take that action
um
this kind of evidence accumulation if
it's occurring via sophisticated effect
of inference
um that this would be a way of
understanding it
and that um part of what would influence
how much buildup or not you get
would be the specifics of
this basically deep tree search
from sophisticated and that we would
might understand the sophisticated
effect of inference
as being orchestrated about hippocampal
and enterorinal system
as iterative mental stimulation where
you're sampling out these different
possibilities of
what would it be like if i move my arm
or not and then you're then evaluating
that in your plant you're spinning
peeling off these different
counterfactuals
and that if across these um you get
enough um
affective charge associated with going
down some of these forks
eventually this results in threshold
crossing but the idea would be that so
this would be relevant to some of the
hippocampal
slam work and that you can think of this
uh imaginative planning stage leading up
to even seemingly spontaneous actions
you can think of this like a magic to
face as being largely orchestrated
by
the hippocampal system which might be
best understood as a
general system for
uh or a system for generalized foraging
and mapping
i don't know if that makes sense but
that's like some of the connections well
if you still want to come for the guest
stream you're welcome to do so
um no that thanks for the awesome
summary and i know that we'll be able to
unpack it a lot more next week um
blue or steven what are some like last
thoughts what was exciting
or interesting to you in where we've
been and where shall we forage next
so i can go i i yeah i was really
interested in taking this into like
semantic space and i wonder what other
kind of spaces that we can maybe
think about mapping out um
how we build how we construct maps
cognitive space and so forth and i'm
excited to um talk to tim about where
where emergence fits into the
hierarchical model
awesome thank you blue steven
yeah i think keeping the
the idea of
keeping things clean keeping things
nascent
and deflatory
even in this case here is really
something i think to continue looking at
and i
i'm really curious about what happens
when we see that door
and that door says you can go down that
corridor
am i going to go down into a different
regime of attention am i going to stay
where i am so i i think
that that ability to
take
these principles
and say okay what is it that happens
when i encounter something and it
triggers something
how much is that
significant in terms of making things
happen and i'm curious then how that can
marry with a lot of the
mental space work that i do building out
metaphor landscapes or actually letting
someone explore
spatially
and one last thing actually that came up
and someone said to me the other day is
there's really curious why when he picks
up his plastic pencil it doesn't mean as
much to him as when he holds a shell
so there's something about like when
that door
has got some prior there's something
that you know about being in a woodland
versus being somewhere which is dead
and even that itself could explain a lot
about
how navigating those places the
eco-psychology of
going into a wooded space a living place
actually can be important for
people
in just in a wellness what might seem a
very woo-woo
type of stuff actually
could be somehow linked to what we're
talking about here so yeah brilliant
thanks
awesome
yeah very
exciting and fun
discussion
i really like that last piece which is
what i know i'm gonna
carry forward and hopefully reflect on
next week
how will we build that colony
is it a memory palace blueprint
is it stigmatic coordination but
how and so somewhere between the
um mental
palace cathedral
and the sort of picking up pebbles and
having no bigger picture is where we are
in our cognitive and social maps and so
that's quite an area and
adam the central complex modeling i
can't wait
so
thank you all for joining thanks tim
also so adam stephen and blue and sid
and dean in the chat so thanks everybody
and see you next time
you